Guide to the Victor Remer Historical Archives of the Children's Aid Society 1836-2006 (bulk 1853-1947) MS 111
New-York Historical Society
- Series V - Diaries, Memoirs, and Historical Sketches by CAS Employees, circa 1853-circa 1980s
  - Subseries V.2 - Short Memoirs by CAS Executives and Employees, 1853-1938
    - Clara Comstock, placing-out agent, memoir/address to CAS staff, and Helen Baxter's introductory remarks. Also a letter from Clara Comstock (poor photocopy) on her experiences, 1935 and circa 1931 or 1932 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - Memoir by Dr. Charles Conklin, Medical Director (2 pages of original missing, but complete photocopy), 1940 February 21 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    - Memoir by Pauline Robinson on history of Monday Sewing Class (photocopy only), 1957 March 21 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 8)
    - Oral history told by Helen Cole, Director of Foster Home Department 1924-1938, circa 1980's (Offsite-box 23, Folder 9)
  - Subseries V.3 - Historical Sketches of the CAS
    This subseries contains 8 folders of short histories and chronologies of CAS events. They may have been composed either to provide internal reference and institutional memory, or as drafts for eventual inclusion in annual reports, appeals, or other public relations documents, although the intended purpose of each document is not clear. Most folders contain several histories. In contrast to the previous subseries of personal memoirs, the authors of the historical sketches are unknown.
    - Histories of the Children's Aid Society (4 documents), 1860-1908 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
    - "A Brief Sketch of the CAS" unfinished draft, 57 pages, circa 1907 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 11)
    - "Notes on Interview with Dr. Conklin" (a history of the Sick Children's Mission/Medical Department), circa 1923-1930 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 12)
    - Histories of the CAS as it relates to Horatio Alger (2 documents), 1928, 1938 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 13)
    - Histories of the Children's Aid Society (3 documents), 1935-1938 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 14)
    - Chronologies of CAS Property and Facilities, undated and circa 1953 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 15)
    - Histories of the Children's Aid Society (2 documents), 1958 and circa 1950's (Offsite-box 23, Folder 16)
    - Histories of the Children's Aid Society (2 documents), undated (Offsite-box 23, Folder 17)
- Series VI - Financial and Fund-Raising Records, 1853-1974
  This series is divided into four subseries:
  VI.1 - Fund-Raising Records
  VI.2 - General Business Documents
  VI.3 - Volumes
  VI.4 - Volumes. Supplement. (Added in July 2018)
  The records in this series were generated in the main offices of the CAS and document the general financial operations of the CAS; for records of finances related to and produced by individual facilities, see Series IX. Materials are arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  Subseries VI.1, Fund-Raising Records, contains diverse types of material, including appeals, pamphlets, brochures, invitations, books, case studies, and correspondence, and is subdivided into four sub-subseries. Three of the four sub-subseries include material generated by the CAS, and the third sub-subseries includes material received and collected by the CAS. (One of these sub-subseries, that with fundraising albums, was added to the finding aid in Aapril 2019.)
  Subseries VI.2, General Business Documents, includes one box of miscellaneous folders and two boxes of file cards detailing payroll at CAS centers 1907-1938.
  Subseries VI.3, Volumes, consists of 207 volumes that were in the originally accumulated and processed collection.
  Subseries VI.4, Volumes - Supplement, consists of 310 volumes added to the original collection in July 2018.
  (Since Annual Reports and other reports produced for the public were also designed to generate donations, see also Series III for examples of that type of fund-raising document).
  - Subseries VI.1 - Fund-Raising Records, 1853-1974
    VI.1.A - Appeals, Pamphlets, Brochures, Invitations, and Books sent to donors, arranged chronologically 1854-1949 and undated
    VI.1.B - Appeals and Case Studies from the files of Margaret Fellows, appeals and publicity director, arranged by facility 1931-1945 (Margaret Fellows collected stories of children's cases and used them to encourage donations)
    VI.1.C - Donation Correspondence (includes letters, notes, and business cards), 1864-1885
    VI.1.D - Fundraising Appeals Albums (includes scrapbook-like albums with samples of appeal letters, forms, and the like, with some clippings), 1924-1974
    - Sub-Subseries VI.1.A: Appeals, Pamphlets, Brochures, Invitations, and Books sent to donors, 1853-1949 and undated
      The sub-subseries contains appeals, pamphlets, brochures, invitations, and books sent to donors, arranged chronologically 1854-1949 and undated. Pamphlets produced for clients may be found in Series IX and Series X, arranged according to the facilities or programs that produced them.
      - Donation/subscription form with overview of first year of CAS accomplishments, 1854 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1)
      - Invitation to first anniversary celebration, 1854 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 2)
      - Appeal to churches, 1861 January 25 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3)
      - 3 appeals, 1868 and undated, 1868, circa 1855-1862, circa 1870-1872 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 4)
      - Appeal to raise funds for a lodging house for boys on E. 11th Street [Eleventh Ward Lodging House], circa 1870 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5)
      - Christmas appeals and replies (2), 1874 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 6)
      - Appeal with reply, 1876 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 7)
      - Christmas appeal, 1879 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 8)
      - Christmas appeals and replies (7), 1880 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 9)
      - Appeal in German, 1880 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 10)
      - Appeals with treasurer's calculations on reverse, 1880 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 11)
      - Christmas appeals and replies, 1884 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 12)
      - Christmas appeal, 1890 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 13)
      - Offer of sale of lantern photographs by Charles Loring Brace II to fund CAS programs, circa 1894-1917 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 14)
      - Appeals for donations to summer charities, 1896 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 15)
      - Christmas appeal, 1896 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 16)
      - Receipt for donation, 1901 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 17)
      - Invitation to an exhibition of the work of the children of the Industrial Schools, 1903 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 18)
      - Draft of appeal, circa 1904 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 19)
      - Pamphlet (fund-raising): Fresh Air programs of CAS, 1905 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 20)
      - Pamphlet: Christmas appeal, 1906 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 21)
      - Pamphlet: Christmas appeal, 1909 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 22)
      - Fund-raising pamphlet, general, 1910 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 23)
      - Fund-raising letter, 1910 May 16 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 24)
      - Book to raise funds for Kip's Bay Boys' Club, 1919 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 25)
      - Pamphlets requesting donations to send newsboys to summer camp (2 pamphlets - photocopies only), circa 1919-1920 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 26)
      - Pamphlet (fund-raising): Kip's Bay Boys' Club, 1920 November (Offsite-box 24, Folder 27)
      - "A Co-Operative Venture in Boy Guidance": Book to raise funds for Kip's Bay Boys' Club, 1924 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 28)
      - Fund-raising pamphlet, general, 1924 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 29)
      - Pamphlet (fund-raising): Nutrition Program, circa 1920's (Offsite-box 24, Folder 30)
      - Pamphlet (fund-raising): Nutrition Program, circa 1920's (Offsite-box 24, Folder 31)
      - Program for Trustees' Dinner, 1928 December 11 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 32)
      - Book to raise funds to turn Bowdoin Farm into a summer camp, circa 1928-1935 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 33)
      - Book to raise funds to turn Bowdoin Farm into a summer camp: "An Adventure in Child Saving", circa 1928-1935 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 34)
      - Book to raise funds for Kip's Bay Boys' Club and fund raising letter to accompany it, 1930 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 35)
      - Book to raise funds for West Side Children's Center (2), circa 1928-1935 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 36)
      - Fund-raising pamphlet for Bowdoin Camp, 1931 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 37)
      - Fund-raising pamphlet, circa 1931-1949 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 38)
      - Christmas appeal, circa 1931-1949 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 39)
      - "The Forgotten Boy" - Booklet to raise funds for Newsboys House and Farm Training (2 copies - very fragile - and photocopy), 1933 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 40)
      - "Between Two Fairs" - General Fund-Raising Pamphlet, 1939 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 41)
      - "Meet a Foster Father" - Fund-Raising Pamphlet for Foster Home Dept., 1939 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 42)
      - "Off Harlem's Streets" - Book to Raise Funds for Harlem Boys' Club, 1940 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 43)
      - "Our Most Defenseless Americans" - Fund-Raising Pamphlet, Homeless Children's Committee, 1941 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 44)
      - CAS Charity Stamps, AKA "Cinderella Stamps", - Seals for promotional/fund-raising purpose, 1943-1949 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 45)
      - "Life Without Mother" - Fund-Raising Pamphlet, 10th Anniversary of Homemaker Services, circa 1943 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 46)
      - Invitation to Exhibition and Gala for Homemaker Service Fundraiser, 1949 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 47)
      - Contribution card for donors to Bowdoin Farm, circa 1929-1940's (Offsite-box 24, Folder 48)
    - Sub-Subseries VI.1.B: Appeals and Case Stories from the files of Margaret Fellows, 1935-1945
      The sub-subseries contains appeals and case stories from the files of Margaret Fellows, Appeals and Publicity Director, arranged alphabetically by facility 1935-1945. Margaret Fellows collected stories of children in the care of the CAS and used the stories to publicize the CAS' good results and encourage donations. Some of the folders contain appeals and case studies; others have only case studies.
      - Brace and Bowdoin Farm - appeals and case studies (includes photo), 1935-1942 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 49)
      - Convalescent Homes - appeals and case studies, 1937-1948 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 50)
      - Counseling and Employment Services - case studies, 1938-1942 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 51)
      - Foster Home Dept. - appeals and case studies (includes photo), 1935-1946 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 52)
      - Housekeeper Service - case studies, 1938 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 53)
      - James Center - case studies, 1939-1941 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 54)
      - Jones Center - case studies, 1939-1947 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 55)
      - Harlem Center - case studies, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 56)
      - Lower West Side (Sullivan Street) Center - case studies, 1939-1947 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 57)
      - Newsboys Lodging House - case studies, 1938 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 58)
      - Walkill Camp - case studies, 1941-1945 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 59)
      - West Side Center, incl. West Side Service for Servicemen and Women - case studies, 1942-1944 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 60)
      - miscellaneous cases, 1941-1945 and undated (Offsite-box 24, Folder 61)
    - Sub-Subseries VI.1.C: Donation Correspondence, 1864-1885
      The sub-subseries consists of 9 boxes of letters, notes, and business cards which accompanied donations to the CAS from 1864-1885. Some years are not represented. The correspondence was originally glued or posted into volumes. The volumes have been disbound, and the glue and backing have been removed from the correspondence. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
      - Donation Correspondence, 1864 February-1865 July (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1865 December (Offsite-box 25, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, circa 1865-1866 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1866 January-April (Offsite-box 25, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1867 December-1868 January (Offsite-box 25, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1867 December-1868 February (Offsite-box 25, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1867 December-1868 February (Offsite-box 25, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1867 December-1868 March (Offsite-box 25, Folder 8)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1868 January-February (Offsite-box 25, Folder 9)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1868 March-July (Offsite-box 25, Folder 10)
      - Donation Correspondence and Alphabetical Key to donation Correspondence December 1867-October 1868, 1868 July-October (Offsite-box 25, Folder 11)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1869 August-December (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 January (Offsite-box 26, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 February (Offsite-box 26, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 March (Offsite-box 26, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 April-May (Offsite-box 26, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 June-November (Offsite-box 26, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 December (Offsite-box 26, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 December (Offsite-box 26, Folder 8)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1870 December (Offsite-box 26, Folder 9)
      - Donation Correspondence, undated, circa 1870 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 10)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1871 January (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1871 January (Offsite-box 27, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1871 February (Offsite-box 27, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1871 March (Offsite-box 27, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1871 April-May (Offsite-box 27, Folder 5)
      - Alphabetical key to donation correspondence and cover of volume that bound correspondence, 1870 November-1871 May (Offsite-box 27, Folder 6)
      - Alphabetical key to donation correspondence and cover of volume that bound correspondence, 1870 December-1871 January (Offsite-box 27, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1872 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 8)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 August-November (Offsite-box 27, Folder 9)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1873 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 5)
      - Alphabetical key to donation correspondence and cover of volume that bound correspondence, 1873 August-December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 February (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 March (Offsite-box 29, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 April-May (Offsite-box 29, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 June (Offsite-box 29, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 July (Offsite-box 29, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 September (Offsite-box 29, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 October-November (Offsite-box 29, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 December (Offsite-box 29, Folder 8)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1874 December (Offsite-box 29, Folder 9)
      - Alphabetical key to donation correspondence and cover of volume that bound correspondence, 1874 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 10)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 June-July (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 July-October (Offsite-box 30, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 October-December (Offsite-box 30, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 December (Offsite-box 30, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 December (Offsite-box 30, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1876 December (Offsite-box 30, Folder 6)
      - Alphabetical key to donation correspondence and cover of volume that bound correspondence, 1876 June-December (Offsite-box 30, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1879 June-August (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1879 September-November (Offsite-box 31, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1879 December (Offsite-box 31, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1879 December (Offsite-box 31, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1879 December (Offsite-box 31, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, undated, circa 1879 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical A-C, 1880 December-1881 January (Offsite-box 31, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical D-J, 1880 December-1881 January (Offsite-box 31, Folder 8)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical K-Q, 1880 December-1881 January (Offsite-box 32, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical R-Z, 1880 December-1881 January (Offsite-box 32, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical A-C, 1881 January 15-December 1 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical D-J, 1881 January 15-December 1 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical K-Q, 1881 January 15-December 1 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, disbound volume, alphabetical R-Z, 1881 January 15-December 1 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1883-1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 1)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 2)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 3)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 4)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 5)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 6)
      - Donation Correspondence, December 1884 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 7)
      - Donation Correspondence, 1885 January-February (Offsite-box 33, Folder 8)
    - Sub-Subseries VI.1.D. Fundraising Appeals Albums, 1924-1974
      The sub-subseries includes scrapbook-like albums with a large number of samples of the various forms, letters, ephemera, annual reports, stamps, etc. used in fundraising appeals for the General Fund and for special purposes. Many of the albums also record information about each fundraising effort, including target audience, number of mailings, response rates and revenue raised, and other information. Year to year comparisons are also present in some cases.
      The sub-subseries is arranged chronologically.
      Note on fragility and condition of the material: Although the individual fundraising documents themselves are in good condition, the albums are deteriorated. The page backings are crumbling and the glue that originally held many of the documents to the backing has loosened, especially for the albums of the 1950s-1970s. Consequently, many documents lie loose in the albums and so must be handled and pages turned with great care. For earlier albums, various fasteners were used to hold the documents in place; most of these were left in the album during processing. To the extent these impede the use of individual documents, patrons should bring that to the attention of the reference librarian who will call for assistance to remove fasteners as needed.
      - Appeals Album, 1924-1929, 1932 (Offsite-box 997, Folder 1)
        Holds only a small number of items for 1924-1926, with bulk of documents from later years. 1932 documents are at back of album, after 1927-1929. 1930-1931 were in a different album (see box 998).
      - Appeals Album, 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 998, Folder 1)
      - Appeals Album, 1933 (Offsite-box 999, Folder 1)
      - Appeals Album, 1934 (Offsite-box 999, Folder 2)
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1937 (Offsite-box 1000, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1938 (Offsite-box 1001, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album, 1939 (Offsite-box 1002, Folder 1)
      - Opera Benefits Album, 1937-1941 (Offsite-box 1002, Folder 2)
        In addition to various opera benefits at the Metropolitan Opera Houses, also includes documents related to the 1940 benefit for the Housekeeper Service Committee, featuring Kirsten Flagstad at Carnegie Hall.
      - Flagstad Benefit Concert Album, 1940 (Offsite-box 1018, Folder 1)
        Includes clippings and summary of publicity in connection with the Kirsten Flagstad benefit performance at Carnegie Hall. See also box 1002, folder 2.
      - Opera Benefits. Clippings, 1940-1941, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 1018, Folder 2)
        Binder of clippings regarding the benefits: "Louise" (1941) and "Die Walkuere" (1944) at the Metropolitan Opera Company, and "The Mermaids Singing" (1945) at the Empire Theatre for the Homemaker Service.
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1940 (Offsite-box 1003, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1942 (Offsite-box 1004, Folder 1-2)
        Although the sample solicitation letters and other fundraising documents in this album are all from 1942, summaries of mailings and returns for both 1941 and 1942 are here.
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1943 (Offsite-box 1005, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1945 (Offsite-box 1006, Folder 1-2)
        Although the sample solicitation letters and other fundraising documents in this album are all from 1945, summaries of mailings and returns for both 1944 and 1945 are here.
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1946 (Offsite-box 1007, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album (2 folders), 1949 (Offsite-box 1008, Folder 1-2)
      - Appeals Album, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 1009, Folder 1)
      - Appeals Album, 1952 (Offsite-box 1009, Folder 2)
      - Order Sample Book (Album), 1952-1959 (Offsite-box 1010)
      - FR [Fundraising] - Appeals: Special Appeals, 1950-1960 (Offsite-box 1017, Folder 1)
      - Samples of Appeals (3 folders), 1951-1964 (Offsite-box 1017, Folder 2-4)
      - Letter Sample Book (Album), 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 1011, Folder 1)
      - Appeals Album, 1963 December-1964 (Offsite-box 1012, Folder 2)
      - Sample Book (Album), 1965 (Offsite-box 1013)
      - Sample Appeals (Album), 1966 (Offsite-box 1013, Folder 2)
      - Sample Appeals (Album), 1967 (Offsite-box 1014)
      - Sample Appeals (Album), 1968 (Offsite-box 1015)
      - Appeal Samples, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 1017, Folder 5)
      - Appeals Album, 1969 (Offsite-box 1015, Folder 2)
      - Appeals Album, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 1016, Folder 1)
      - Appeals Album, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 1016, Folder 2)
      - Appeals Album, 1974 (Offsite-box 1016, Folder 3)
  - Subseries VI.2 - General Business Documents, 1864-1938 and undated
    This subseries consists of 1 box of miscellaneous documents, including some loose pages separated from bound volumes, relating to financial matters such as donations, expenses, payroll, and other matters, 1864-1936 and undated, arranged chronologically, followed by 2 boxes (boxes 35 and 36) of 5x8 index cards detailing employee salaries at CAS centers, September 1907-June 1938, arranged in their original order. The original order is as follows: Box 35 contains cards detailing Teachers' Payroll September 1907-February 1926 in reverse chronological order. Box 36 contains cards detailing teacher's payroll March-1926-July 1932 in reverse chronological order, followed by payroll from the Columbus Hill Center November 1928-Augsut 1930, followed by Mr. Johnson's Department payrolls March 1931-June 1938, and finally Mr. Gilson's Department Payrolls January 1934-June 1938